<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Abouts on Econometrics and Free Software</title>
    <link>/about/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Abouts on Econometrics and Free Software</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    
	<atom:link href="/about/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>/about/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/projects/</guid>
      <description>Functional programming and unit testing for data munging with R I am currently writing a book about functional programming, unit testing and package development with R. You can read it for free here and you can buy a digital copy at leanpub.
Gumbel Linux I am developing a custom GNU+Linux iso aimed at statisticians/data scientists/econometricians. It&amp;rsquo;ll have everything needed pre-installed. I did this in the past already, by using Suse Studio.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Research</title>
      <link>/about/research/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/research/</guid>
      <description>Published Articles Version Control Systems to Facilitate Research Collaboration in Economics, in Computational Economics, 2015 Abstract
Reliable and reproducible research is an important cornerstone of science, and version control systems not only make reproducible research possible in a rapid and easy way, but also provide a way of collaborating with co-authors. The purpose of this methodological paper is to present Git, a very successful version control system and how it can be used by economists working together on their papers and the accompanying computer code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software</title>
      <link>/about/software/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/software/</guid>
      <description>This is a list of software I use for work. I only use Free Software (whenever I have a choice, at least). Free here is not about price, but about freedom. Think of free as in free speech. The reasons I chose to use free software are both practical and philosophical. Free software gives me infinite flexibility: I can install it on any machine I own without having to worry about licenses or worry that the software may become deprecated some day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Who am I?</title>
      <link>/about/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/about/</guid>
      <description>My name is Bruno Rodrigues and I am a PhD candidate at the Bureau d’économie Théorique et Appliquée at the University of Strasbourg. My thesis advisor is Bertrand Kœbel and my co-advisor is François Laisney.
I started working at STATEC, which is the national statistical office of the Grand-Duchy of Luxembourg in July 2016. I&amp;rsquo;m part of the research division and my main mission is assisting the researchers with data issues.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>